Finding Aid for Dick M. Jacobs Papers, 1980-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dick M. Jacobs Papers 1980-1993
Jacobs, Dick M., 1938-1993.
1.5 linear foot
9469 Aa 2
Holland, Michigan businessman, member of the Libertarian party and candidate for various public offices in Michigan in the years 1982-1992. Jacobs was involved in tax cut initiatives and organizations. Biographical materials, files detailing his efforts in writing and supporting tax reduction amendments, political campaign files, and records of the Taxpayers Association of Michigan, an organization founded by Jacobs and concerned with tax reduction and term limitations for elected officials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Carol Jacobs and family (Donor No. 8246 ) in April 1994.
The collection is open to research.
Dick Morrell Jacobs was born December 26, 1938, in Owosso, Michigan. After graduating from Central Michigan University in 1962 with a B.S. in Liberal Arts, Jacobs held sales positions in various Michigan-based companies. He began his own construction-supply marketing firm, D.M. Jacobs and Associates, in Grand Blanc, Michigan, in 1971. Jacobs shut down the company's operations in 1984 and joined Management Recruiters as a consultant from 1985 to 1987. The following year, he launched a consulting and recruiting firm, Data Research, in Holland, Michigan, where he served as president until his death in 1993.
Even before beginning his own career in politics, Jacobs was an active member of the Libertarian Party. Issues related to taxes received much of his attention. From 1980 to 1982, he wrote a weekly column for the Grand Blanc News Weekly, "Citizens Taxpayer" that discussed taxes and government issues. He assisted fellow libertarian Robert Tisch in drafting and promoting Tisch's initiative tax cut amendment to Michigan's Constitution in 1980. The next year, Jacobs established the Jacobs Tax Reduction Committee and created his own initiative petition tax cut amendment. In 1990, he founded the Taxpayers Association of Michigan, a statewide, nonprofit and nonpartisan organization. One of the projects that the association sponsored was an initiative petition to limit politicians' terms, which was co-written by Jacobs and passed in November 1991. In 1992, Jacobs co-authored another such petition, "Citizens to Lower and Limit Taxes." The group did not obtain the signatures necessary to secure its placement on the ballot, however.
Jacobs ran for public office five times between 1982 and 1992. In 1982, he ran for governor of Michigan as a libertarian but was defeated. He tried to unseat Donald Riegle from the United States Senate, again representing the Libertarian Party, in 1988. The 1990 election found Jacobs briefly switching his allegiances to the Republican party and entering the state Senate race. He was eliminated from the race during the primaries. Undeterred by the loss, Jacobs entered the gubernatorial race as an independent, the result of a write-in campaign. Once more, he was defeated in the election. He ran for office a final time in 1992, as a libertarian in the congressional race.
In 1986, Jacobs was diagnosed with a rare form of cancer. Despite a bleak prognosis, the political activist managed to survive nearly twice as long as expected and wage several campaigns for public office. Jacobs accepted no radiation for the cancer; instead, he received some degree of treatment at the Immunology Research Centre in the Bahamas. Jacobs died June 26, 1993, at his home in Holland, Michigan, at the age of 54.
The Dick M. Jacobs Papers document Jacobs's political and professional activities from 1980 to 1993. Records in the collection are divided into three series: Biographical Material, Political Activities, and the Taxpayers Association of Michigan.
Subjects:
Elections--Michigan--1982.; Elections--Michigan--1988.; Elections--Michigan--1990.; Elections--Michigan--1992.; Jacobs, Dick M., 1938-1993.; Libertarian Party of Michigan.; Taxpayers Association of Michigan.; Tax and expenditure limitations--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Jacobs, Dick M., 1938-1993.; Political elections--Michigan--1982.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical Material
  Biographical Material consists of one folder, which includes data sheets, resumes, biographical statements in campaign literature, and clippings.
  - Data sheets and biographical statements (Box 1)
- Political Activities
  Composing the bulk of the collection, the Political Activities series is further divided into the following subseries: Initiative Petitions, Statements, Gubernatorial Campaign, 1982, Ron Paul Campaign Correspondence, U.S. Senatorial Campaign, 1988, Non-Campaign-Related Materials, State Senate/Gubernatorial Campaigns, 1990, and Congressional Campaign, 1992. Within the Initiative Petitions subseries, there are four folders containing material documenting Jacobs's role in writing and promoting Robert Tisch's proposed state tax reduction amendments and later his own version of a tax reduction amendment. The Statements subseries contains Jacobs's views on such topics as the state of American democracy, the need for and future of the Libertarian Party, and Michigan's economy.
  Material from Jacobs's five political campaigns make up the remaining subseries. These are arranged chronologically by campaign: Gubernatorial, 1982; U.S. Senatorial Campaign, 1988; State Senate/Gubernatorial Campaigns, 1990; and Congressional Campaign, 1990. Highlights of the material include a folder of miscellanea from the 1982 gubernatorial effort that contains unlabelled photographs of Jacobs greeting people on the campaign trail. This folder also contains Jacobs's political literature, sample ballots, and documents pertaining to the election results.
  Also of special interest is the correspondence in the subseries, State Senate/Gubernatorial Campaigns, 1990, which conveys the opinions of Jacobs's Libertarian counterparts toward his temporary switch to the Republican party and his personal rationale behind the change. Records from the 1992 congressional campaign include a folder of surveys and questionnaires that Jacobs completed during the campaign. Due to several undated materials in this folder, they are arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization that sent them. Other documents of note include a folder of Jacobs's political statements and campaign-related notes, arranged chronologically, as well as several undated statements.
  Another folder includes correspondence and other material generated by Jacobs in support of Libertarian candidate Ron Paul's 1988 presidential campaign. A folder of material from 1989, which is not related to any of his campaigns, includes correspondence documenting Jacobs's ballot initiative regarding the development of a school-voucher system and a property tax reduction initiative, his support of salary cuts for federal officials, and the creation of a Michigan citizens' organization to stage petition drives. These records are arranged chronologically.
  - Initiative Petitions
    - Tisch Tax Cut Amendments and Related Material
      - 1980-1981 undated (Box 1)
      - Clippings 1980-1982 (Box 1)
    - Jacobs Tax Cut Amendment and Related Material 1981, undated (Box 1)
    - Jacobs Tax Reduction Committee
      - Financial Reports 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Statements undated (Box 1)
  - Gubernatorial Campaign 1982
    - Campaign Miscellany (Box 1)
    - Candidate Surveys and Responses, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Clippings
      - January-April 1982 (Box 1)
      - May-August 1982 (Box 1)
      - September 1982-April 1983 (Box 1)
    - Weekly Columns and Related Material
      - February-December 1980 (Box 1)
      - January 1981-January 1982 undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - March-December 1980 (Box 1)
      - January-December 1981 undated (Box 1)
      - January-March 1982 (Box 1)
      - April-August 1982 (Box 1)
      - September-November 1982 (Box 1)
    - Financial Reports (Box 1)
    - Lawsuit Documents (Box 1)
    - Newsletter Articles (Box 1)
    - Statement Samples 1982, undated (Box 1)
  - Ron Paul Campaign Correspondence (Box 1)
  - U.S. Senatorial Campaign 1988
    - Campaign Miscellanea (Box 1)
    - Candidate Surveys and Responses (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Undated (Box 1)
      - May 1987 January-March 1988 (Box 1)
      - April-June 1988 (Box 1)
      - July-September 1988 (Box 1)
      - October-December 1988 (Box 1)
    - Financial Reports (Box 1)
    - Newsletter Articles (Box 1)
    - Newsletters (Box 1)
    - Press Releases (Box 1)
    - Schedule Samples (Box 1)
    - Statement Samples (Box 1)
  - Non-Campaign-Related Materials December 1988-December 1989 (Box 2)
  - State Senate/Gubernatorial Campaigns 1990
    - Campaign Miscellanea (Box 2)
    - Candidate Surveys and Responses (Box 2)
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - Undated (Box 2)
      - February-December 1990 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters (Box 2)
    - Press Releases (Box 2)
  - Congressional Campaign 1992
    - Candidate Surveys and Responses (Box 2)
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - January-July 1992 undated (Box 2)
      - August-December 1992 (Box 2)
    - Press Releases (Box 2)
    - Sample Ballots (Box 2)
    - Statement Samples and Notes (Box 2)
- Taxpayers Association of Michigan
  Of particular note in the Taxpayers Association of Michigan material is a folder of miscellaneous documents relating to the organization. The folder includes official statements of organization, samples of promotional literature, and a sample district representative agreement contract. One folder of undated and six folders of dated and chronologically arranged correspondence document Jacobs's activities in the association. Highlights from the 1990 correspondence include letters reflecting Jacobs's efforts to begin a new alternative political party, the Taxpayers Party. The folders of materials from 1991 include letters pertaining to the organization's development of an initiative petition to limit the terms of state officials. It also documents Jacobs's opposition to the Persian Gulf War, reflected in letters to former President George Bush. Correspondence relating to the organization's initiative petition project, Citizens to Limit and Lower Taxes, is located in the folders of 1992 material.
  - Bylaws and Articles of Incorporation (Box 2)
  - Association Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Clippings
    - 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1990 (Box 2)
    - January-March 1991 (Box 2)
    - April-June 1991 (Box 2)
    - July-September 1991 (Box 2)
    - October-December 1991 (Box 2)
    - January-March 1992 (Box 2)
    - April-December 1992 (Box 2)
  - Initiative Petitions and Related Material Undated (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    - 1991 undated (Box 2)
    - 1992 undated (Box 2)
  - Notes 1991, undated (Box 2)
  - Press Releases 1990-1992 (Box 2)
  - Statement Sample 1991 (Box 2)
  - Surveys and Responses 1991-1992 (Box 2)